Rhys Caparn Papers
Rhys Caparn Papers
1932-1973
Caparn, Rhys, 1909-1997.
3 linear ft.
Correspondence (1932-1967); original sketches, photographs, and reproductions of her artwork; essays and notes for an art column; and printed material, including articles and reviews about Caparn (1933-1963), clippings (1935-1970), exhibition catalogs, invitations, and posters (1939-1973). Correspondents include Alexander Archipenko, Doris Caesar, George Constant, Lyonel Feininger, Sidney Gordin, Joseph Konzal, Theodore J. Roszak, Helena Simkhovitch, and Mitzi Solomon.
148887
Biographical History
American sculptor, illustrator, former president of the Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1932 to 1973, the Rhys Caparn Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the American sculptor, educator, and former president of the Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors (b. 1909). The collection illuminates Caparn's personal life and the evolution of her artistic career.
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence-subject files (Boxes 1-3) consists of incoming letters and outgoing holograph drafts and typescript carbons, as well as other documents relating to artwork. Among the correspondents are the architectural firm R. B. O'Connor and W. H. Kilham, Jr.; fellow artists (Rifka Angel, Alexander Archipenko, Helen Beling, Doris Caesar, George Constant, Paula Eliasoph, Dorothy Lubell Feigin, Lyonel Feininger, Perle Fine, Sidney Gordin, Joseph Konzal, Pauline Elizabeth Law, Naomi Lorne, Leon Gordon Miller, Paul Mommer, Edouard Navellier, Marianna Pineda, Edward Renouf, Theodore J. Roszak, Henry Schonbauer, Helena Simkhovitch, Mitzi Solomon, Beulah Stevenson, Challis Walker, Jane Wasey, Arline Wingate); clients (Barnard College, H. Bittner and Company, Campagna Construction Corporation, Farrar, Straus & Young, Otto Gerson, Mildred Gosman, Elizabeth Huston, Irene Kraft, Morton D. May, Alice Rosenfeld, Jimmie Savo, William R. Scott, Inc., Sculpture-in-Replica, Ralph Walker); and museum directors (John Phillips Coolidge, Bartlett Harding Hayes, James Johnson Sweeney). Organizational correspondence includes that of art associations (American Artists' Congress, American Federation of Arts, Artists for CORE, Artists for Victory, Brooklyn Society of Artists, Committee of Artists' Societies, Fairmount Park Art Association, Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, National Association of Women Artists, School Art League of New York City, Sculptors Guild); art galleries and museums (American Museum of Natural History, Arden Galleries, Art Center in La Jolla, Bonestell Gallery, Brooklyn Museum, Country Art Gallery, Gotham Gallery of Contemporary Art, Guild Hall, Hansa Art Gallery, John Heller Gallery, Tirca Karlis Gallery, Meltzer Gallery, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, Museum of Modern Art, New York State Fair Art Center, Norfolk Museum, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, Petit Palais, Riverside Museum, Silvermine Guild of Artists, Whitney Museum of American Art, Wildenstein & Co.); educational institutions (Adelphi College, Dalton Schools, Dartmouth College, Philadelphia Museum College of Art, Smith College, Syracuse University, University of Nebraska); and government agencies (New York City Office of Cultural Affairs, United States Department of State).
Artwork (Box 4) encompasses original sketches, photographs, and reproductions of Caparn's works. Photographs include those of drawings (arranged by title when available), exhibitions (1950-1970), and sculpture, which is subdivided by general works (in alphabetical order by title provided by Caparn), and portraits (arranged by name of person). Essays written for an art column, Notes pertaining to exhibitions, and miscellaneous Essays and Notes on art constitute Writings (Box 4).
Memorabilia (Boxes 5-6) consists of membership cards, miscellaneous receipts, a partial inventory of artwork (with prices), photographs of Caparn, and printed material. Printed material comprises articles and reviews about Caparn (1933-1963), newspaper clippings (1935-1970), exhibition catalogs and invitations for group (1939-1970) and one-person shows (1947-1973), as well as several exhibition posters. There is a also one audiorecording.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Archipenko, Alexander, 1887-1964.; Caesar, Doris, 1893-1971.; Caparn, Rhys, 1909-1997.; Constant, George, 1892-; Cunliffe, Mitzi Solomon, 1918-; Feininger, Lyonel, 1871-1956.; Gordin, Sidney, 1918-; Konzal, Joseph.; Roszak, Theodore, 1907-1981.; Simkhovitch, Helena.; Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Illustrators -- United States.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Women artists -- United States.; Women sculptors -- United States.; Articles.; Audiocassettes.; Sound recordings.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Sketches.; Artists.; Illustrators.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Rhys Caparn, 1964, 1971, 1972.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Adelphi College (Garden City, N.Y.), 1960 (Box 1)
  - American Artists' Congress, Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1940 (Box 1)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1940-1963 (Box 1)
  - American Museum of Natural History (New York, N.Y.), 1951; 1958 (Box 1)
  - Angel, Rifka, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Archipenko, Alexander, 1934-1958; undated (Box 1)
  - Arden Galleries Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Argent Galleries (New York, N.Y.), See National Association of Women Artists, Inc.
  - Art Center in La Jolla (La Jolla, Calif.), 1958 (Box 1)
  - Art Digest, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Art News, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Artists for CORE (New York, N.Y.), 1964 (Box 1)
  - Artists for Victory, Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1942-1944 (Box 1)
  - Barnard College (New York, N.Y.), 1958-1960; undated (Box 1)
    See also R. B. O'Connor and W. H. Kilham, Jr.
  - Beling, Helen, undated (Box 1)
  - H. Bittner and Company (New York, N.Y.), undated (Box 1)
  - Bonestell Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1940 (Box 1)
  - Brandt, Kathleen Weil-Garris, 1953; 1958 (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Museum, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Society of Artists, Inc., 1954 (Box 1)
  - Caesar, Doris, undated (Box 1)
  - Campagna Construction Corporation (New York, N.Y.), 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Cellini Bronze Works Co. (Brooklyn, N.Y.), 1940; 1941 (Box 1)
  - Columbia Pictures Corporation (New York, N.Y.), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Committee of Artists' Societies (New York, N.Y.), 1963-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Congress of Racial Equality (New York, N.Y.), See Artists for CORE
  - Constant, George, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Coolidge, John Phillips, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Council of Jewish Women (Englewood, N.J.), 1963 (Box 1)
  - Country Art Gallery (Westbury, N.Y.), 1954-1955; undated (Box 1)
  - Dalton Schools (New York, N.Y.), 1946-1964 (Box 1)
  - Danbury Hospital (Danbury, Conn.), 1967 (Box 1)
  - Dartmouth College (Hanover, N.H.), 1948-1957 (Box 1)
  - Eliasoph, Paula, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Fairmount Park Art Association (Philadelphia, Pa.), 1949 (Box 1)
  - Farrar, Straus & Young, Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1953 (Box 1)
  - Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors (New York, N.Y.), 1940-1960; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Feigin, Dorothy Lubell, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Feininger, Lyonel, 1941-1946 (Box 1)
  - Fine, Perle, 1948; undated (Box 1)
  - Four O'Clock Forums (New York, N.Y.), 1954 (Box 1)
  - Gerson, Otto, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Gordin, Sidney, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Gosman, Mildred, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Gotham Gallery of Contemporary Art (New Hope, Pa.), 1961 (Box 2)
  - Guild Hall (East Hampton, N.Y.), 1952-1963 (Box 2)
  - Hansa Art Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1954 (Box 2)
  - Hayes, Bartlett Harding, 1944 (Box 2)
  - John Heller Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1952 (Box 2)
  - Huston, Elizabeth, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Isaacs, Stanley M., 1958 (Box 2)
  - Junior Literary Guild (New York, N.Y.), 1962; 1963 (Box 2)
  - Tirca Karlis Gallery (Provincetown, Mass.), 1961 (Box 2)
  - Konzal, Joseph, undated (Box 2)
  - Kraft, Irene, 1953; undated (Box 2)
  - Lahr, Jane, 1962; 1963 (Box 2)
  - Law, Pauline Elizabeth, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Lieber, Stephanie, 1950-1953 (Box 2)
  - Lorne, Naomi, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Macy, Gertrude, 1941 (Box 2)
  - May, Morton D., 1953-1957; undated (Box 2)
  - Meltzer, Doris, See Meltzer Gallery
  - Meltzer Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1956-1963 (Box 2)
  - Mental Health Association of Essex County (East Orange, N.J.), undated (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.), 1945-1955 (Box 2)
  - Miller, Leon Gordon, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - Mommer, Paul, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute (Utica, N.Y.), 1955-1959 (Box 2)
  - Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.), 1941-1953; undated (Box 2)
  - National Association of Women Artists, Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1946-1948; undated (Box 2)
  - National Serigraph Society (New York, N.Y.), See Meltzer Gallery
  - Navellier, Edouard, 1932 (Box 2)
  - New York City. Office of Cultural Affairs, 1952; 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - New York State Fair. Art Center, 1958 (Box 2)
  - New York World's Fair, See Committee of Artists' Societies
  - Norfolk Museum (Norfolk, Va.), 1963 (Box 2)
  - R. B. O'Connor and W. H. Kilham, Jr., Architects (New York, N.Y.), 1957-1960; undated (Box 2)
  - Offin, Charles Z., See Pictures on Exhibit
  - Pellegrini & Cudahy (New York, N.Y.), See Farrar, Straus & Young, Inc.
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1952-1961; undated (Box 2)
  - Petit Palais (Paris, France), 1949-1950; undated (Box 2)
    See also Lieber, Stephanie
  - Philadelphia Museum. College of Art - 1960 (Box 2)
  - Pictures on Exhibit, undated (Box 2)
  - Pineda, Marianna, 1964; undated (Box 2)
  - Pousette-Dart, Nathaniel, See Farrar, Straus & Young, Inc.
  - C. J. Reid & Co., Inc. Insurance (New York, N.Y.), 1958 (Box 2)
  - Renouf, Edward, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Riverside Museum (New York, N.Y.), 1953-1965 (Box 2)
  - Roman Bronze Works, Inc. (Corona, N.Y.), 1947 (Box 2)
  - Rosenfeld, Alice, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Roszak, Theodore J., 1963 (Box 2)
  - Royall, Kenneth C., 1953; 1960 (Box 2)
  - Savo, Jimmie, 1943? (Box 3)
  - Schapiro, Meyer, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Scholastic Magazines Art Awards (New York, N.Y.), 1962 (Box 3)
  - Schonbauer, Henry, 1956 (Box 3)
  - School Art League of New York City (Brooklyn, N.Y.), 1958-1963 (Box 3)
  - William R. Scott, Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1962; 1963,; undated (Box 3)
  - Sculptors Guild, Incorporated (New York, N.Y.), 1948-1953; undated (Box 3)
  - Sculpture-in-Replica (Park Forest, Ill.), 1949-1953; undated (Box 3)
  - Silvermine Guild of Artists Incorporated (Norwalk, Conn.), 1954 (Box 3)
  - Simkhovitch, Helena, undated (Box 3)
  - Smith College (Northampton, Mass.), 1940; 1951 (Box 3)
  - Solomon, Mitzi, 1947; undated (Box 3)
  - Stevenson, Beulah, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Sweeney, James Johnson, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - Tacke, Reinhard R., 1948; 1950 (Box 3)
  - United States. Department of State, 1960 (Box 3)
  - University of Nebraska, 1952; 1962 (Box 3)
  - Valentin, Curt, 1952 (Box 3)
  - WNYC (radio and television), See New York City. Office of Cultural Affairs
  - Walker, Challis, 1943; undated (Box 3)
  - Walker, Ralph, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Wasey, Jane, 1953; 1958,; undated (Box 3)
  - Weil-Garris, Kathleen, See Brandt, Kathleen Weil-Garris
  - Whitney Museum of American Art (New York, N.Y.), 1940; 1952-1955 (Box 3)
  - Wildenstein & Co. (New York, N.Y.), 1944-1951; undated (Box 3)
  - Willard, Marian, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Wingate, Arline, 1948; 1950,; undated (Box 3)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 3)
- Artwork
  - Photographs
    - Drawings
      - By title - A-Z (Box 4)
      - Untitled, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
    - Exhibitions, 1950-1970 (Box 4)
    - Sculpture
      - General (by title) - A-Z, multiple titles, untitled, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Portraits (by name of person) - A-Z (Box 4)
  - Reproductions, 1944-1969; undated (Box 4)
  - Sketches (original)
    - Crayon and pencil, undated; 11 items (Box 4)
    - Pencil, undated; 1 item (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Essays
    - Art column, 1966-1967; undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Notes
    - Exhibition-related - statement on sculpture, titles of artwork (with prices) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Membership cards, miscellaneous receipts (Box 5)
  - Partial inventory of artwork (with prices) (Box 5)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 5)
  - Printed material
    - Articles, reviews, 1933-1963; undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1935-1970; undated (Box 5)
    - Exhibition catalogs, invitations
      - Group shows, 1939-1957; 3 folders of 9 (Box 5)
      - Group shows, 1939-1957; 6 folders of 9 (Box 6)
      - One-person shows, 1947-1973; undated (Box 6)
    - Exhibition posters, 1960; 1963,; undated (Box 6)
  - World of the Arts (dub), 1/6/64; caparn_r_001; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - Miscellany (Box 6)